Okay בקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is ק"ד, Kuf Dalet,
104. We pick up at the very bottom of ק"ג עמוד ב,
Kuf Gimmel Amud Bet, after the משנה. Mishnah.
The משנה Mishnah said that if somebody is selling somebody a plot
of land and he says I'm selling you this plot of land
and it's a בית כור, Beit Kor, which is we said did
the math, I forget, oh did I erase it? Well whatever it
is. Anyway, okay, it's 30 סאה, Seah, I think somebody said it
was about four acres or something. I think we said what did
we say, like football fields or something?
One of seven acres to ten?
All right, so whatever it is. All right. All right. Anyways is
a little bit larger than a football field and you say that
you're selling that to the person. So if you say that you're
doing it מידה בחבל, Mida Bechevel, measured by the yardstick, effectively, exact,
precise, then any amount that's off you have to basically, you know,
make it good. You have to, if the guy got a little
bit too much he gives back the land if that's relevant or
he pays the difference in the price. If he got too little
he gets a discount and so on. That's if it's, that's if
he says precise, it's got to be precise. If however he says
more or less, okay, then you're allowed to be off by it
says a רובע לסאה, Rova Leseah, which is
1/24th. Okay, there's 24 רבעים, Reva'im, there's it's a רובע הקב Rova
Hakav and there's six קב Kav to a סאה. Seah. So you're
allowed to be off basically 1/24th of the total, either more or
less. If however it's more than the 1/24th, it says then you
have to make good, you have to even it up and you're
then not only evening up the overage, you're evening up the entire,
you know, the entire amount. Okay, so you know, it's not just
if it was like, you know, if it was instead of being
1/24th it was 1/20th, well whatever, I'm not going to do it.
Okay, anyway, if you're allowed to be over on one unit and
you were over on 1.1 units, so it's not just that you
make good on the 0.1 unit, you make good on the whole
1.1. All right, so that's basically a summary of the משנה Mishnah
and we'll get to obviously, I skipped over a little part about
like about the prerogative of the מוכר, Mocher, we'll get to that
in the גמרא. Gemara. But before I do, I want to just
point out two things. Number one is the question about why is
it not relevant here the principle of אין אונאה בקרקעות, Ein Ona'ah
Bekarka'ot, that there's no idea of overcharging by קרקע? Karka? So why
isn't all of it, okay, so we have so why don't we
just say it doesn't matter if it's too little, too much or
whatever, overcharging isn't relevant by קרקע? Karka? So as Michael correctly remembered,
אונאה Ona'ah was the principle when you got exactly what you wanted
to get, like you thought you were getting ten apples and you
got ten apples, but the amount that you paid was more than
the normal going rate. Whereas if I wanted to buy ten apples
and you gave me nine, that's not, or you gave me 11,
right, that's not אונאה, Ona'ah, that's actually a more or less amount
of what I was expecting to get. So אונאה Ona'ah isn't relevant
there.
So we have so why don't we just say it doesn't matter
by issues of like מידה ומשקל Mida Vemishkal and so on. Okay
fine, so we're saying but then what we say is that it's
ביטול מקח. Bitul Mekach. If you know, if you were supposed to
get a certain quantity and you got more or less, we normally
say that the whole sale is void. How come here we say
that the sale is good but you just have to make up
the difference, right? Because normally we say that either it's the principle
of אונאה Ona'ah or it's the principle of ביטול מקח. Bitul Mekach.
So if we say that when you're off it's not, you know,
it's this is not what I was expecting to get, the whole
sale should be voided. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says we assume that
by קרקע Karka people, you know, are not, you know, don't want
to void the whole sale. They like they fundamentally either fundamentally they
really do want this plot of land or they understand that sometimes
it could be off by a little bit. So therefore there's like
not a, you know, there's not this principle of מקח טעות Mekach
Ta'ut doesn't operate in the same way when you're off a little
bit by קרקע. Karka. That's what the רשב"ם Rashbam says. תוספות Tosafot
says no no, in general it would be but there's two types
and this is really what's important, two types of being off. Okay,
one type of being off, let's look at this תוספות, Tosafot, okay,
if you look at תוספות פחות כלשהו ינכה, Tosafot Pachot Kolshehu Yenakeh,
at the top of ק"ד עמוד א, Kuf Dalet Amud Alef, תוספות
Tosafot says the following. Okay,
it's like two lines down in the narrow lines of that תוספות,
Tosafot, the last word on the line, ואומר ר"י Ve'omer Ri דרבא
De-Rava when he says it if you're off by the amount of
a number or the measure, it's a מקח טעות, Mekach Ta'ut, דרבא
איירי כשמדדו והטעו במידה De-Rava ayiri k'shemadedu vehite'u bemida that basically you
said oh we're going to measure it and I go and I
take out the measure and I say okay I sent out my
engineers there or my surveyors and they measured it and it was
one and a half acres. And then you go and you see
that I pulled the wool over your eyes, it was one and
a quarter acres. Okay, so then we say מקח טעות. Mekach Ta'ut.
I really say that I've measured it, this is the amount, and
I'm lying. Okay, or even if I'm not intentionally lying, but at
least you know there's a claim that it's been measured and that
it's different than what that claim is. So that's a real like
that's a real gap in the understanding and therefore it's a מקח
טעות, Mekach Ta'ut, even without the deception part. But אבל הכא, Aval
Hacha, yeah presumably, אבל הכא... Aval Hacha... הכא לא מדדו אדיין אלא
בבואין למדוד ומתחילה נמי הוה ידוע שאינו מכוון כל כך שלא יהיה
או פחות או יותר. hacha lo medadu adayin ella bivayin limdod umitchila
nami hava yadua she'eino mechunan kol kach shelo yiheyeh o pachot o
yoter. So there's this case and in another תוספות Tosafos he says
you're standing in the middle of the field and you're saying like
I'm going to sell you this field. We all know it hasn't
been measured and I say it's a בית כור beit kor or
I say it's about a בית כור. beit kor. Okay, so in
those types of cases we all know implicitly that it's not going
to be exact, I'm not claiming a precision. We haven't exactly measured
it yet. So he says in that type of a case that's
not a case where we say that if you're off by the
number or the weight or whatever it's a מקח טעות mekach to'us
because he says that starts by a sense that there's been a
precise measurement and then it's different than that precise measurement. In this
case where it's never been measured and you are from the very
beginning it's implicit that you're imprecise, you're estimating or so on. So
you know so in those types of cases he says there's no
מקח טעות. mekach to'us. It's interesting even if I say I am
selling you this field which is a בית כור beit kor by
exact measurement, what that's interpreted to mean according to the way תוספות
Tosafos understands it is not that I have exactly measured it and
it's a בית כור. beit kor. If you said that and you
were off it would be a מקח טעות. mekach to'us. What you're
saying is that by saying I am selling you this and it's
a בית כור beit kor by exact measurement, what I'm saying is
if it's off even the slightest amount we'll even it up. Okay,
but I'm not claiming that it is precisely a בית כור. beit
kor. If I'm claiming that I've measured it and it's precisely and
I'm off then תוספות Tosafos says that would be מקח טעות. mekach
to'us. But if it's known that it's not yet been measured then
it depends. So if I say it's a בית כור beit kor
or more or less a בית כור beit kor whatever I said
then it allows a certain tolerance before we have to make it
up. If I say a בית כור beit kor exactly then I
make up any difference, but it's still there's no claim yet that
it's been precisely measured. Yes,
David.
The question of אונאה ona'ah by קרקע, karka, isn't there a concept
of market value by קרקע? karka? What? Isn't there a concept of
market value?
Yeah, yeah, I mean part of the reason there's no אונאה ona'ah
by קרקע karka might be גזירת הכתוב gezeirat hakatuv and it might
also be because there's a lot of land speculation so there's not
as much of a fixed market value. Okay, but that's if the
price was different, here the amount is different. Okay, yeah.
Maybe discussed this yesterday, but in the משנה mishnah
it says מהו מחזיר לו מעות. mahu machzir lo ma'ot. Is that
just going on the second part or even on the first part?
Yeah, so that's a good point. I didn't discuss it because you're
right, but let's wait until we get to the גמרא gemara but
you're right logically it should go just as much on the first
part. Once there's an evening up, it shouldn't matter which direction. I
understand, yeah,
I didn't see a discussion about that in the גמרא gemara and
the ראשונים rishonim but I agree with you. Okay, let's continue. Anyway,
that's just one principal point I wanted to make which is you
know how does this fit into the אונאה ona'ah issue and to
the ביטול מקח bitul mekach issue. And that תוספות Tosafos understands and
this is going to be relevant as we continue that this case
is that you're basically in the field, you know the field you're
talking about but you don't know the exact measure. Okay, but if
there's a claim that it's been exactly measured and then it's off,
that's a different story. Let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara.
Okay, so
איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, there is the following question. בית כור סתם
מאי? beit kor stam mai? Let's say somebody did not say it's
a בית כור beit kor precisely and but they also didn't say
more or less. They just said I'm selling you a בית כור,
beit kor, right? No modifiers.
Do we say even if it's off the slightest amount you have
to make it good, you have to even it up? Or do
we have that tolerance of that one twenty-fourth? So the גמרא gemara
says תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. בית כור עפר אני
מוכר לך מידה בחבל. beit kor afar ani mocher lach mida bechevel.
Let's look at our משנה. mishnah. It says if you say a
בית כור beit kor measured by the yardstick, in that case פחות
כל שהוא ינכה יתר כל שהוא יחזיר. pachot kol shehu yinakeh yeter
kol shehu yachzir. So in that case if it's a little bit
less or a little bit more even the tiniest amount you have
to even it up. So that's because you said precisely, you said
by the measuring stick. הא סתם, ha stam, if you just said
a בית כור beit kor without any modifier, כהן חסר הן יתר
דמי, kehen chaser hen yeter dami, it's like you said more or
less. Okay, since the משנה mishnah says that when you say measured
by the measuring stick it implies that without any modifier you're allowed
a certain you know tolerance, you're allowed to be off by a
little bit amount. So the גמרא gemara says אימא סיפא, eima seifa,
no, because obviously this is the whole point, this is the problem
of the excluded middle. Let's look at the end case. ואם אמר
לו הן חסר הן יתר, ve'im amar lo hen chaser hen yeter,
if you say more or less, אפילו פיחת רובע לסאה או הותיר
רובע לסאה הגיעו, afilu pichat rova les'ah o hotir rova les'ah higi'o,
then if they're off even by a רובע rova to a סאה,
se'ah, meaning one twenty-fourth, you have to swallow it either way. So
that's only with that modifier you have to swallow it. הא סתם,
ha stam, if you didn't say anything, כמידה בחבל דמי, kemida bechevel
dami, then it's implicitly like you said precise. Okay, so that's the
whole reason we're asking the question because the משנה mishnah gives the
two extremes and it doesn't give the middle. It says if you
say more or less then you have tolerance. If you say exact
you have no tolerance. What if you say neither? So the גמרא
gemara says אלא מהא ליכא למשמע מינה, ella meha leika lemishma mina,
fine. From our משנה mishnah we don't know the middle case. תא
שמע, ta shema, come and hear, we have a ברייתא. braita. בית
כור עפר אני מוכר לך. beit kor afar ani mocher lach. So
if you say בית כור עפר אני
מוכר לך. beit kor afar ani mocher lach. בית כור עפר, beit
kor afar, כבית כור עפר אני מוכר לך. ke-veit kor afar ani
mocher lach. I'm selling you like a בית כור עפר, beit kor
afar, approximately a בית כור. beit kor. הן חסר הן יתר אני
מוכר לך. Hen chaser hen yeter ani mocher lach. I'm selling it
to you more or less. So it sounds like you say any
of those three languages. I'm selling you a בית כור, beit kor,
I'm selling you approximately a בית כור, beit kor, I'm selling you
a בית כור beit kor give or take. Okay, any of those.
So in any of those cases, what does it say? אפילו פיחת
רובע לסאה הותיר רובע לסאה הגיעו. afillu picheis rova le-se'ah hotzir rova
le-se'ah higiyo. Even if you're off by a רובע rova to a
סאה se'ah in either direction, 1/24th, you have to swallow it. So
it's explicit. It says any one of those three languages allows for
you to be off by a little bit. Okay? And including in
them is just the סתם stam case, no modifier. So the גמרא
Gemara says,
let's just answer like we usually do, נסיקא?
nasika? Alright, that's fine. That's what we're going to say. Very good,
Michael. אלמא, Alma, but that's not פשט. pshat. Anyway, okay, אלמא סתם
נמי כהן חסר הן יתר דמי. alma stam nami ke-hen chaser hen
yeter dami. So you see, even without any modifier, it's like you
said, more or less. It's explicit, it gives you three cases, one
of them is that you didn't have any modifier. The גמרא Gemara
says והתם פירושי קמפרש. ve-hasam peirushei kam-fareish. No, we can read that
as not being three separate cases, but as as modifying the first
claim. איזו בית כור שהוא כבית כור? Eizu beit kor she-hu ke-veit
kor? It says בית כור אני מוכר לך, beit kor ani mocher
lach, כבית כור אני מוכר לך. ke-veit kor ani mocher lach. So
what is a when you say בית כור, beit kor, is it
like you said, approximately a בית כור? beit kor? כגון דאמר ליה
הן חסר הן יתר. kegon de-amar lei hen chaser hen yeter. If
you said more or less. Okay, which is obviously not פשט. pshat.
Right? It says if you say בית כור, beit kor, like a
בית כור, beit kor, more or less. So what it's actually saying
is you take the first and the third and you combine them.
A בית כור beit kor plus more or less equals the second
case when you said approximately a בית כור. beit kor. So obviously
that's not פשט, pshat, but the גמרא Gemara is saying maybe that's
what we're talking about.
מתקיף לה רב אשי. Matkif lah Rav Ashi. So רב אשי Rav
Ashi rejects this. אם כן אני מוכר לך אני מוכר לך למה
לי? Im ken ani mocher lach ani mocher lach lama li? No,
no, no. If it was all basically the same case, it wouldn't
have said בית כור עפר אני מוכר לך, beit kor afar ani
mocher lach, כבית כור עפר אני מוכר לך, ke-veit kor afar ani
mocher lach, you know, הן חסר הן יתר אני מוכר לך. hen
chaser hen yeter ani mocher lach. Saying אני מוכר לך ani mocher
lach after each of those phrases shows we're talking about each one
as a standalone case. אלא שמע מינה סתם נמי כהן חסר הן
יתר דמי. Ela shma mina stam nami ke-hen chaser hen yeter dami.
So you see that without any modifier, it means more or less.
So the גמרא Gemara says שמע מינה. shma mina. So yes, you're
right. That's a good point. Look at that, we actually concluded something.
We don't do that very often.
Yeah, exactly. So even there תוספות Tosafot says sometimes we don't let
that bother us. Okay. Now again, this only makes sense if you
are basically standing in the field and you're looking at the field,
right? Because like, let's say תוספות Tosafot asks the following question. Let's
say I say to Michael, Michael, I'm going to sell you a
you know, I have all these acres, I'll sell you an acre,
okay? Michael says great, and he pays me the money, okay? And
then we go over and I measure him out an acre less
1/24th. Because I just said I'll sell you an acre, so you
know, I'm allowed to be off by 1/24th. So Michael says you
got no, no, no, intentionally! I'm allowed to be off by
so besides the accidentally, the point is, is that there, we were
never talking about a specific field. I was telling if I tell
you I'm going to sell you twelve apples, I have to deliver
twelve apples. If I sell you I'm going to sell you a
בית כור, beit kor, I have to measure out for you a
full בית כור, beit kor, you're right. So the only reason here
you're allowed this tolerance is because fundamentally you're not you know, you're
focused on the object, not on the quantity, not on the size.
We all know we're talking about this field and we all know
what the boundaries of this field is. Now there's a problem, which
is it was a little bit less or a little bit more
than I expected, so we have to make good. But you know,
but again, if I just say to you, I'm going to sell
you a בית כור, beit kor, let's go to my field and
we'll measure it out, I don't say, well, I'm allowed I said
a בית כור, beit kor, I'm allowed to be off by a
little bit, so I'm not going to give you a full בית
כור, beit kor, right? Obviously you can't say that. Here again it
starts fundamentally where you are, you know, where you're what do you
call where you're dealing with the field itself. Look at the תוספות,
Tosafot, I'll give you another תוספות Tosafot that says this, okay?
He
says פחת כל שהוא ינכה, pachas kol she-hu yenake, the second the
next תוספות Tosafot from the top of the דף. daf. So like,
if it's a little bit less, then I get a discount. So
תוספות Tosafot says ואם תאמר ולימא ליה דאדעתא דהכי לא זבני. v-im
tomar ve-leima lei de-adaata de-hachi lo zavni. I don't understand, if we're
off a little if you know, if it's more than 1/24th, then
I get a discount. Why can't I say, no, I only wanted
to buy a full acre, right? If this you know, I don't
want a discount, I want my money back, I wanted a full
acre. Okay? Well, there is no full field to give, this is
the entire field, but I assumed it was an acre. If it's
off what do you mean give me a discount? I don't want
no discount. ויש אומרים דקאי בתוך השדה כדי להפרישו דמעיקרא הוה נמי
יודע שאינו מכוון לגמרי. v-yesh omrim de-kai be-toch ha-sadeh kedei le-hafrishei de-me-ichara
hava nami yodeia she-eino mechuvan le-gamrei. So no, you always we always
knew what we were dealing with, right? So you know, and the
fact so and again, I also presume it's like you could have
measured it also if you wanted to. So again, for תוספות, Tosafot,
and I think it's פשט, pshat, you know, what's important here is
we know the object we're dealing with, okay? And because of that,
there's more tolerance to say that the sale is going to remain
good, even if it's, you know, over, even if it's under, we
don't say
it's a
ביטול מקח. bitul mekach. Because we all know the object, we all
know that unless you measure it you're not going to be exactly
precise about the size, so we're all sort of tolerating a certain
amount of variation. Okay. So yes Michael.
So from what I get here are two things: one is that
it's better to just say this field and not give the measurement.
Yeah, and then you know because then you don't have to deal
with any other adjustment. And
so therefore if it wasn't this field, so even if you said
סתמא, stama, it means exact if it's just say based on based
on what.
Yeah, if you're not standing within the field, I mean, or if
you're not indicating a clear field that we all know we're talking
about, right? You know, like, you know, if you say my apple
orchard, you don't have to be physically standing in it, but we
know the specific concrete field we're talking about. If I just סתם
stam tell you I'll sell you an acre from my wheat field
or whatever, then it's exact, then I have to give you a
full amount. Okay. All right.
So now the סתמא stama היכא דחסר ויתר heicha dechaser veyaser is
only in cases where
you're fundamentally, as I was saying, the case here is to explain
why it's not ביטול מקח bitul mekach and why we allow tolerance
and all of that. The case is that we there's a clear
field with clear boundaries that we know we're talking about and that
starts as the object we're selling. And then how big is it?
We're a little bit, you know, we're a little off. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מהו מחזיר לו מעות. mahu
machzir lo maos.
So now we get to the second part of the משנה. mishna.
When you're off and Michael is correct that the משנה mishna frames
this as when you said more or less and then you're off
by more than 1/24th, how you make good. But in theory this
could be the exact same discussion if you said precisely and you're
off by even a little bit. How do you make good? Okay.
So if the although I didn't see
the תוספות Tosfos say that explicitly. So
if the buyer got too little, okay, then there's only one way
to make good, which is I give him a
discount. And תוספות Tosfos already said, you know, this issue how come
you can't say like hey I thought I was getting a full
amount I don't want it. No, you knew what you were talking
about. So but if it was less than the promised amount, you
know, then the expected amount, the בית כור, beis kor, then he
gets a discount. All right, so that's if the buyer gets too
little. Let's say the buyer got too much. What does he give
me back? Does he give me back the extra land or does
he give me back the difference in the money? So the משנה
mishna said it's my choice. Okay, the we benefit the מוכר, mocher,
the מוכר mocher gets to say if I want the land back,
I get the land back, which is the logical thing. I gave
you too much land, give me the land back, right? But what
am I going to do with a tiny little piece of land?
So if I want to I can say give me back the
money. Now
the second part of the משנה mishna said however if the extra
land that I gave Michael there was objectively a large enough size
to be a little plot by itself, then I don't have the
choice to say give me back the money. Then Michael gives me
back the land and that's the end of it. But if it's
such a small size that it's not meaningful to use that by
itself, to plow that, to tend to that by itself, then I
have the choice to say I'd rather have the money than the
land. All right, so let's take a look at what the גמרא
Gemara says.
So has the seller the choice where he wants that in the
area then?
What do you mean?
The seller, if he's getting some land back? Yes. Can he tell
the buyer I want that area over here or...
Oh, that's a good question, that's an excellent question. Who gets to
decide which part of that land it goes back? Yeah, I would
imagine that that would be the buyer's choice, right? Because the buyer
basically, yeah, that's a really good question. Joe, your phone there...
But it wouldn't make sense if they're like okay, keep that part
right in the middle of the field.
Right, right, right. No, I'm saying I think it would be the
buyer's choice. The buyer got the whole thing, right? He's giving it
back, right? I would think he would get to... it's a really
good question. I don't know why it wasn't raised, but it's a
really good question.
What I'm trying to say is if
he has a choice you can't say all right, you know. Yeah,
but you can say this end or that end or whatever.
You can't say like okay, go take the part smack in the
middle. Right, and now you have to buy the right of way,
right? You know. No, I understand.
So you're saying there could be some limits on that. Right, but
it's still a really good question. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this, okay: מהו מחזיר לו מעות. mahu machzir lo maos. So
the גמרא Gemara says: ליפה כוחו של מוכר אמרינן ליפה כוחו של
לוקח לא אמרינן? leyafe kocho shel mocher amrinan leyafe kocho shel lokeach
lo amrinan? Are you saying that it's only the מוכר mocher has
a prerogative and not the buyer when it's a little bit extra
land? והתניא, vehatanya, we taught in a ברייתא: braisa: פיחת שבעה קבין
ומחצה לכור, pichas shiva kabin u-mechtza le-kor, or הותיר שבעה קבין ומחצה
לכור, hosir shiva kabin u-mechtza le-kor, הגיעו. higiyo. If it's up to
1/24th, seven and a half קב kav for a כור, kor, translates
into seven and a half קב. kav. Okay, so if you're selling
the whole big כור, kor, you can do the math, we did
the math the other day, it translates into seven and a half
קב. kav. That's the tolerable amount for a כור kor to be
over. So it says: פיחת
שבעה קבין ומחצה לכור pichas shiva kabin u-mechtza le-kor or הותיר שבעה
קבין ומחצה לכור, hosir shiva kabin u-mechtza le-kor, הגיעו. higiyo. If it's
up to
1/24th, seven and a half קב, kav, then you gotta swallow it.
If you're under or over.
יותר מכאן, yoser mikan, if it's more than seven and a half,
so it's beyond a tolerable amount, כופין את המוכר למכור ואת הלוקח
ליקח. kofin es ha-mocher limkor ve-es ha-lokeach likach. You force the seller
to sell and the buyer to buy. So now, first of all,
it doesn't mean both of them. Like what are we? We're gonna
force both, the seller to sell, the buyer to buy, and they
both just want to give back the money? No, but it means
either way, meaning that we have a preference to say just that
the buyer should have it all and pay up the difference in
money. So if either of them want that, if the buyer wants
to keep the land, the extra land, and the seller doesn't want
to sell it, you force the seller to sell him the extra
land. Okay, and if the seller wants to want to
have the buyer keep the land but the buyer doesn't, then you
force the buyer then you force the buyer to keep land meaning
it's a way of saying if either side wants this land to
go with the buyer, then you're gonna make that happen even if
the other side doesn't want it. We have a we have a
bias towards doing that, which makes sense, right, to not have a
little sliver of land there, you know, belonging to the original owner,
it makes sense to say look, you know, at the end of
the day it's gonna be much better for everybody or whatever, you
know, we חזל Chazal maybe social engineers or whatever it is, you
know, but or but saying like you know, as long as one
side wants it, the other side needs
to—Does it depend if it's contiguous with your field?
Well, we're gonna get to that actually. Right, if it's contiguous your
field it could be different. But if it's not contiguous your field
and the buyer's gonna have a little sliver right next to the
seller I mean if the seller's gonna have a little sliver right
next to the buyer's like large field like that's considered to be
like you know if either side can claim that's not in my
best interest and we would be sensitive to that claim and therefore
we would we would try to we would force the other side
to go along with it. So that's at least what the ברייתא
braisa says. The ברייתא braisa says is if either side wants that
wants to just pay money you know wants this field wants the
sliver to go with the buyer, you make that happen. But that's
against our משנה. mishna. Our משנה mishna says it's totally the buyer's
choice, okay? So how are we gonna reconcile this with our משנה?
mishna? The seller's choice, excuse me, I keep on getting okay, fine.
It's totally the seller's choice. Okay, so how do you reconcile this
with our משנה? mishna? So the גמרא Gemara says let's read it
again. יותר מכאן Yoser mikan כופין את המוכר למכור kofin es hamocher
limkor if it's more than that then you force the seller to
sell even if he didn't want to as long as the buyer
wants that sliver of land. ואת הלוקח ליקח V'es halokeach likach you
force the buyer to buy even if he really didn't want to
as long as the seller says I can't use that little piece
of land. Okay, so so that's saying that either one has a
right to demand the to demand that the little sliver goes with
the rest of the land. As opposed to our משנה mishna where
it says it's the seller's prerogative. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
התם hasam that's not what it means. Of course it is what
it means but okay, that's not what it means. התם Hasam כגון
דהוי יקירא מעיקרא וזיל השתא.
k'gon de-havei yakira me-ikara v-zil hashta.
It originally was expensive and now it's worth less. דאמרינן ליה De-amrinan
leh אי ארעא יהבת ליה ee ara yahat leh
we say to the to the seller if you want to give
him the land, הבת ליה כזולא דהשתא. havt leh kezola de-hashta. You
have to give him the lower price now, which means what? Which
means let's say okay, I was told that I don't have this
okay, that this didn't get up here. Let's say
okay,
here is my
כור, kor, okay? Here's the little extra I mean it's not a
little it doesn't it didn't start that way obviously or else yeah
we'll do it a little bit more realistically. Okay, so I was
talking about this whole land and we realize that this was a
כור kor and this amount here was like you know eighth קב,
kav, okay? There, that's the extra amount. I don't know the question
that David asks like how do we decide that's the extra amount
and not that and not that and not that? Good question. Okay,
fine. So anyway, alright, so that's the extra amount. Now
so
so do we force do we force the guy to buy it
or the seller to sell it? So and so the משנה mishna
the ברייתא braisa again the ברייתא braisa the משנה mishna sounds like
it's the seller's prerogative, the ברייתא braisa sounds like we give every
either side the option to demand that that small piece goes with
the rest of the piece. So the גמרא Gemara says no no
no, we're gonna take it like the משנה, mishna, that it's totally
the seller's prerogative. Okay, but what's the case? The case was that
initially the price of the field here was I don't know was
like a thousand dollars, okay? Was a thousand dollars. So the price
of this little amount here would have been ten dollars, let's say,
okay? That was the initial, that was when it was sold. Now
land prices have gone down, okay? And now the price of this
whole thing is eight eight hundred dollars and now this whole this
is worth eight, okay? Now I'm the seller.
I want Michael to buy it. I say I don't want that
little sliver of land, what can I use that little sliver of
land for? I want you to buy it. So according to משנה
mishna that's my prerogative, right? I can make him buy it. But
yeah, I want him to buy it at ten dollars, at the
old rate. Okay? So the so what the ברייתא braisa is saying
is no, if you want to sell it to Michael, which you
don't have to, you can just say to Michael like you know,
I gave you extra land that at the time was worth ten
dollars, you know Give me an extra ten dollars, give me ten
dollars back because at the time of the sale, at the time
of the sale he got a ten dollar bonus. Right? Is that
clear? So at the time of the sale he got a ten
dollar bonus. So if I want to get the money back I
say, give me back the ten dollars. Okay? That's fine. But if
you want to... wait, did I say that right? Yes, give me
an extra ten dollars because that's how much it was worth at
the time of the sale. But if I want to... wait, am
I saying this right? I gave Michael too much. No, I'm sorry,
I made the same mistake. Excuse me, excuse me. One more time.
Okay, here we go again. Okay. So I gave Michael too much.
So
if
what should have been is that he just gives
me back that sliver of land. Okay? I shouldn't have given him
that sliver of land and therefore the base is just give me
back that sliver of land. If I want him to take it
now and to buy it, we look then at a transaction that's
happening now because the starting point is that he should give me
back that sliver of land. Okay. So if he wants to buy,
I want him to buy it, give it back to me now,
you know, buy it now. So therefore he can say, fine, I'll
buy it from you but I'll buy it at today's rate. And
I say, no, I want you to buy it at the same
rate I sold it to you at. I'm not entitled to do
that. So the ברייתא braisa that says we force the seller to
sell does not mean according to this that we force the seller
to sell. It's still totally my prerogative. I could say give me
the land or I could say I'm forcing you to buy. What
it means that we force me to sell is that if I'm
selling, we force me to sell at today's rate. I don't get
the right to sell at the original rate. All right. So the
buyer can never... it's never the buyer's prerogative, it's always the seller's.
I can always ask for either the land or for the money
but the force the seller to sell means if I'm choosing to
sell, which I can be free not to, I'm free to take
the land back, but if I'm choosing to sell, then I have
to sell at the lower rates of today, not the higher rates
of when it was originally bought. So let's read that
again. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. התם כגון דהוה יקירא מעיקרא, hasam ke-gon de-hava yakira me-ikara, originally
it was the land was worth more, וזיל השתא, ve-zil hashta, now
it's less. ואמרינן ליה, ve-amrinan lei, so we say to the מוכר.
mocher. Again, it's never the buyer's prerogative, always the מוכר. mocher. So
we say, you want your land back? Be my guest. But if
you want to sell it to the buyer now, אי ארעא יהבת
ליה, ei arai yavis lei, if you're choosing to sell that extra
land to the buyer, הוי כזולא דהשתא, havei ke-zola de-hashta, you got
to sell it to him at today's lower prices. Okay. And therefore,
force the seller to sell never means the basic choice of selling,
that's all in the seller's prerogative, but it means if you're selling,
we're forcing you to sell at the lower price. Yes, Eli asks
a question.
אדי מוכר למכור ולוקח ליקח.
adi mocher limkor ve-loke'ach likach.
Right. How are we reading
that?
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to ask. Okay.
So we presume the converse holds true?
Well, we're going to get to, that's exactly what we're going to
get to. Okay. Yeah, but you're right. אדי מוכר למכור adi mocher
limkor means we force you to sell at today's prices and לוקח
ליקח loke'ach likach means we force the buyer to buy. No, not
if he wants, because it's always the seller's prerogative. So it means
different things. It's always the seller's prerogative. So if the seller chooses
to sell, we force him to sell at today's prices and we
force the buyer, if he chooses to sell, we also force the
buyer to buy regardless of price because the buyer never has a
choice. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara says. Okay. Now. והתניא דכי נותן נותן לו כשער שלקח
ממנו. ve-hatanya de-ki she-nosain nosain lo ke-sha'ar she-lakach mimenu. Wait a minute,
but the ברייתא braisa says that if the buyer is buying that
extra sliver of land, it's based on the original price. So the
גמרא Gemara says, התם כגון דהוה זולא מעיקרא ויקירא דהשתא. hasam ke-gon
de-hava zola me-ikara ve-yakira de-hashta. No, that's when it was cheap originally
and now it's more expensive. Okay. So basically it means that if
it's true we're giving the seller the prerogative, but he cannot, the
buyer gets the advantage of the lower price. You want to force
him to buy, so I mean imagine by either way you understand
the claim. In this claim the buyer is saying like you want
me to buy that extra sliver of land off of you? Fine.
I'm not going to pay more than the going rate. Right now
the going rate is eight dollars, not ten dollars. That's a completely
reasonable claim. So we say if you're going to force him to
buy, he gets the right to buy today's low rate. In the
reverse case, okay, where it originally sold for eight hundred, and this
was eight dollars, and now it's going for ten, the buyer can
say you want me to buy that sliver of land? Fine. But
I was only buying the land when it was at the lower
rate. So you can't now force me to buy this extra sliver
at today's new rate. My whole basic purchase was based on the
assumption of the lower rates. So either way the buyer has a
legitimate claim that he should be paying the lower rate, whether it
was
the
original. We're keeping the משנה Mishna that it's the seller's prerogative, and
but we're reading the ברייתא Braita that you force the seller, meaning
that you force the seller to sell it at the lower rate.
Is that like a punishment to the seller in a way for
making a mistake?
I don't know if I'd say it's a punishment. I say since
it's your
prerogative, then, if you're forcing this choice on the buyer, then it's
only balanced by the fact that we're not totally disadvantaging the buyer.
I don't see this as a punishment. I see, no, you don't
like it, fine, give him, take the land back, you know. Right,
but it starts with the fact that we're giving the seller an
advantage, you know.
The final question on this, you know, you're assuming that it's all
like evenly distributed, like, you know, but let's say, oh, well, that's
the one with the river view, that part's not worth...
That just goes back exactly to David's question, which is who gets
to decide
what the extra land is, which is... But then what rate do
you decide it at? You know what I mean?
Oh, that's an interesting point too. That's a good point. Right, meaning
it's related to the question of who gets to decide where the
extra land is is like, but I guess that's once that is
decided then we would figure out how much it costs.
No, but I mean you're looking at like all the land is
even, but maybe parts...
Yeah, fine, you're right, it might not be proportional. You're right. Okay,
so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so now, שאם שייר בשדה בית תשעה קבין, She'im shiyer basadeh
beis tisha kabin, now, now it goes on and says like this.
Now again, for a כור, kor, okay, this is the amount that's
tolerable overage is seven and a half. So actually, this issue of
the prerogative is very limited. When it's seven and a half, so
then the sale is good, okay, then the sale because then it's
tolerable. Once it's anywhere from 7.51
to you know, 8.99, there we say you've got a choice, okay.
You can either get the money or the land back in terms
of the seller. Okay, once it hits nine קב kav and more,
then we say it's only going to be the land. Nine קב
kav we say is a big enough plot to, you know, that's
worth tending to, you know, it's a usable plot of land for
growing wheat or whatever, different amounts for wheat and for vegetables and
so on. So once it's nine קב kav is not a proportion,
it's an absolute amount. Once the overage is nine קב, kav, then
the seller doesn't get a choice. We just say to the seller,
you know, take the plot back, you can use this plot. If
the buyer wants to buy and the seller wants to sell to
the buyer, be my guest, okay. But if the buyer doesn't want
to buy, then he then you don't get a choice. He can
give you that land. You can't say what am I going to
do with a little sliver. Nine קב kav is already a usable
amount. All right, so that's what the משנה Mishna teaches. All right,
so now let's take a look here at the גמרא. Gemara.
So then if he... they would use the current rate, I mean
they'd have to decide on a rate.
No rate, you're giving the land back.
No, no, I'm saying if he decides...
Oh, if he decides then whatever they negotiate. Right.
What they negotiate? Yeah, exactly.
Okay, אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, תשעה קבין שאמרו,
tisha
kabin
she'amru,
when we say nine קב kav that then the no, the seller
has to take it back and doesn't have a prerogative, okay, אפילו
בבקעה גדולה, afilu b'vikah gedolah,
even in a large valley. What he makes is a very logical
point. He says all of this, right, was assuming that it was
a כור kor and one twenty-fourth of a כור kor is seven
and a half קב kav and that's tolerable. He says, let's say
I'm selling somebody a thousand כור, kor, a huge valley, okay. So
in that type of a case,
you know, as soon as it is a as soon as it's
over the tolerable overage, the one twenty-fourth, right, even up to one
twenty-fourth, let's just make it easy. Let's say I'm selling two קב,
kav, okay, I'm selling somebody
two כור. kor. I'm selling double this amount, I'm selling two כור,
kor, okay. So then the one twenty-fourth tolerable amount would be 15
קב kav as opposed to seven and a half. Now even though
15 קב kav is a usable plot of land, it's still a
tolerable off because we've, I've said approximately or I meant approximately, so
the sale is still, you know, you don't do anything. Let's say
it's a smidgen above that. It's 15.1 קב kav over, okay, then
what he's saying is, okay, once it's beyond the tolerable amount and
objectively it's nine קב, kav, I don't, you know, there doesn't have
to be this middle range, all right. Once the plot of land
that you're that that's over and it's no longer tolerable is nine
קב, kav, then the buyer has then the seller has to take
it. He doesn't have a prerogative, he can use that plot of
land. Okay, so that's the point where he says, תשעה קבין שאמרו
אפילו בבקעה גדולה, tisha kabin she'amru afilu b'vikah gedolah,
that it's it doesn't remain proportional. You don't say if this is
two כור kor then when it's within this range times two, 15
to 18, then it's still the buyer it's still the seller's prerogative.
Why is it the seller's prerogative if it's 15 to 18? It's
a big enough plot. Big enough plot of land, let him take
it back. All right? So that's what he says, אפילו בקעה גדולה.
afilu bik'ah gedolah. רב נחמן אמר, Rav Nachman amar, no, נושא שבעה
קבין ומחצה לכל כור וכור. nosei shiva kabin u'mechtzah lechol kor ve'kor.
He says no, I disagree. He says I basically say that if
it is, okay, you multiply it, okay? So that if this is,
which is a strange idea, but he basically says that if it's
two כור, kor, then up to 15, fine sale. 15, between 15
and 18, okay, seller's prerogative. Once it hits 18, then it has
to be the land. You look at each thing as a separate,
as a separate כור, kor, which really is a very strange idea.
Okay, you like this דף daf here? No תוספות, Tosafot, huge רשב"ם.
Rashbam. It's actually not such a hard דף, daf, but the רשב"ם
Rashbam spends a lot of time rejecting other interpretations of the גמרא.
Gemara. Okay, but the actual way the רשב"ם Rashbam reads the גמרא
Gemara is pretty straightforward. So let's keep on going. ואי איכא מידי
יתירא לתשעה קבין הדרי. ve'ei ika midi yateira l'tisha kabin hadri. Okay,
now he says...
Now I have to remember if I'm reading this right. Hold on
one
second. Right. So what he basically says is that, right, right. So
he says the key of reading this is that לתשעה קבין l'tisha
kabin means means per כור. kor. He says for you look at,
even if you were selling two כור, kor, okay, you look at
each כור kor individually. So you say if the whole amount over
was you know was 15 or was 14, you say okay so
then that is we divide that by the number of כור. kor.
So per כור, kor, if it was less than seven and a
half, keeps the land. If it's between, you know, it's a done
deal. If it's between per כור kor seven and a half and
nine, it's the seller's prerogative. If it's more than nine, then he
has to take the land back. But you don't look at that
as the total amount, you look at it as the per כור
kor amount. Okay? So that's what he says ואי איכא מילתא יתירא
לתשעה קבין, ve'ei ika milta yateira l'tisha kabin, if there's more than
nine קב, kav, again the keywords here that you have to read
in is per כור, kor, then הדרי, hadri, then it goes back.
So the basic difference is where I totally, I gotta tell you,
I totally side here with רב הונא, Rav Huna, although we're not
gonna פסקן pasken that way. We're gonna פסקן pasken like רב נחמן.
Rav Nachman. But רב הונא Rav Huna
basically says, he says this issue is an absolute amount. So if
it's two כור kor that you're selling, up to 15 קב kav
it's a final sale. 15.1, okay, there's no longer tolerable amount and
15.1 is usable, the seller doesn't have any choice, he takes the
land back. Whereas רב נחמן Rav Nachman says no, you divide it
all by the number of כור. kor. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. איתיביה רבא לרב נחמן. Eitivei Rava le'Rav Nachman.
So רבא Rava asked רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. אם שייר בשדה בית
תשעה קבין. im shayer besadeh beit tisha kabin. So it says the
end of the משנה Mishnah says if you left nine קב kav
over, then the seller has to take it. He doesn't have a
choice. So it says לאו דזבין ליה כוריים? lav d'zavin lei kora'im?
Doesn't it sound like regardless of what the total sale was, it's
saying an absolute amount? Regardless of how much the total amount of
land was being sold, even if you're selling two כור, kor, once
there's nine קב kav of overage, then the seller has to take
it, okay, and doesn't get a prerogative. גמרא Gemara says לא דזבין
ליה כור. lo d'zavin lei kor. No, we're talking about a classic
case of selling just one כור. kor. That's when he has to
take it by nine. But if you're selling two כור, kor, then
you know then it would then it would have to be 18
before the seller would have to take it without a prerogative. Okay,
so גמרא Gemara says like this. וביגנה בית חצי קב. u'vigenah beit
chatzi kav. But the משנה Mishnah continues. It says if you're selling
a vegetable garden, בית חצי קב, beit chatzi kav, then once you
hit a half קב, kav, you are you know then the seller
has to take it. He does not have a prerogative. Okay? So
גמרא Gemara says לאו דזבין ליה סאתיים? lav d'zavin lei sa'atayim? Now
is it not that now
meaning because again, remember the amount you're allowed over is a רובע
rova per סאה. se'ah. Okay? A סאה se'ah is six קב. kav.
Six קב kav a סאה se'ah
and a קב kav is four רובע. rova. So you're allowed 1/24th,
but it's a רובע לסאה. rova l'se'ah. So where it says by
a גינה ginah it says when does the guy have to take
the גינה ginah and he doesn't have the prerogative? So it says
what's the amount it says? וביגנה בית חצי קב, u'vigenah beit chatzi
kav, a half a קב. kav. A half a קב kav is
two רובע, rova, right? רובע rova is a quarter. Okay, so it
says so if this is a סאה, se'ah, so it says if
you're selling him a סאה, se'ah, you're allowed to be off by
A quarter of a קב kav, *kav* here, okay, a quarter of
a קב kav, *kav*, that's final sale
from point
0.251, you know, to a half of a קב kav. *kav*, to
0.499,
that's prerogative, okay, and 0.5 קב kav *kav*, a half of a
קב kav *kav* is only the land. Okay, so the משנה Mishna.
*Mishnah* said that when you're dealing with a גינה gina, *ginah*, a
half of a קב kav *kav* of a גינה *ginah* is a
usable amount, and the guy's gotta take it. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, aren't we talking about the case where you sold a
סאה se'ah, *se'ah*, and when you sold a סאה *se'ah*, then, I'm
sorry, two סאה *se'ah*? That even if you sold two סאה *se'ah*,
right, even if you told two סאה *se'ah*, as soon as you
hit the absolute amount of a half קב *kav*, he would have
to take it. You would not like double, you know, you would
not double the amount, you would not do it proportional. Once you
hit that absolute amount of a usable גינה *ginah* of a half
קב *kav*, he'd have to take it. Aren't we talking about that,
that even if you sold מאי לאו דזבין ליה סאתים *mai lav
dizaven lei se'atayim*? You sold a large plot, and even so, we
don't just multiply it proportional? We say once you hit a half
קב *kav*, he's got to take it? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, לא דזבין ליה סאה *lo dizaven lei se'ah*. No, you sold
a סאה *se'ah*, and that's why it goes by a half קב
*kav*, but if you sold two סאה *se'ah*, then the only amount
of land that he would have to take would be if it
were a full קב *kav*. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* continues. We're just going to do the
same thing with every line of the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. Okay, וכדברי
רבי עקיבא בית רובע rova, *uk'divrei Rabbi Akiva beis rova*. So according
to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, he thinks that a garden can even
be a quarter of a קב *kav* to be usable, and the
seller has to take it. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, מאי לאו
דזבין ליה סאה *mai lav dizaven lei se'ah*? Are we not talking
that you sold a
סאה *se'ah*? And even though, and when you sold, and even though,
again, because according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, now it's all getting
confusing. But according to, according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, let's say
if you sold a סאה *se'ah*,
right, that's this case. רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says בית רובע rova,
*beis rova*, he has to accept a,
right, meaning according to, so according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, you
sold a סאה *se'ah*, alright? So as soon as you hit a
רובע rova קב *rova kav*, meaning it eliminates the middle, right, as
soon as you hit a רובע rova, קב *rova kav*, he says
that's a usable amount. So and that's up to a רובע rova,
קב *rova kav* is like, you know, is tolerable overage. So as
soon as you go over the רובע rova קב *rova kav*, immediately
the seller has to take it. He has, he loses his prerogative.
So you see, so again, there's no, you don't multiply it, it
doesn't have to be that middle space. Once you've hit that amount
that can be usable by itself, okay, so then it's immediately the
seller has to take it, and you don't do proportional to maintain
that middle, that middle zone. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, isn't
that the case? מאי לאו דזבין ליה סאה *mai lav dizaven lei
se'ah*? And even though as soon as you hit that size, that
absolute amount, then he has to take it? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, לא דזבין ליה חצי סאה *lo dizaven lei chatzi se'ah*. No,
it was that he sold a חצי סאה *chatzi se'ah*, and that's
what allows there to be those
ranges.
Well, no, I
mean, what עלי *Eli* says is correct. The משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, the
whole point of the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* seems to be like, these
are the absolute amounts, once the overage hits this absolute amount and
goes beyond the amount of מחילה *mechilah*, the seller has to take
it back, he doesn't have a prerogative. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
right, and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s reading, so thank you for pointing
that out עלי *Eli*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s reading the משנה Mishnah
*Mishnah* that every case is only talking about a, you know, a
different size of the total sale, right, to sort of allow for
this, you know, to allow for the same type of a range
to be maintained. Right? So if it's talking about a חצי סאה
*chatzi se'ah*, right, then this range is allowed up to, this goes
up to basically an eighth, and then you're going to have this
range from an eighth to a quarter, and then this is going
to start at a quarter. So it says, that's our case of
the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*. When the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* says at a
quarter of a קב *kav* he has to take back, that's when
it's the size of the field is such that allows for exactly
those types of ranges. But if the size of the field is
bigger, you know, then he would have to, he wouldn't have to
take it back when it hit a quarter סאה *se'ah*, he'd have
to wait till the total overage was more than a quarter סאה
*se'ah*. Alright, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. I don't
know if that was all so clear, but I think you get
the basic idea. The basic idea is that, I have a sense
that we sort of lost the forest for the trees here, maybe
I don't feel so bad that there's so much רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*.
But anyway, the basic, the basic debate is very clear, okay, that
the case in the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* is that the seller has
the prerogative, and what רב הונא Rav Huna *Rav Huna* says, which
makes an enormous amount of sense is, he loses that prerogative once
the absolute size of the overage is usable. Okay? And it doesn't
matter, you don't have to maintain its proportional, right, it's not proportional.
Once the absolute size of the overage is usable, he loses his
prerogative. And רב נחמן Rav Nachman says, no, you always maintain proportional
to the amount set out in the משנה. Mishnah All right, so
let's see what the גמרא says. בעי רב אשי, Ba’ei Rav Ashi,
רב אשי Rav Ashi asked, שדה ונעשית גינה, גינה ונעשית שדה מאי?
sade ve-na’asis gina, gina ve-na’asis sade mai? תיקו. Teiku. So this was
a, now we understand, this is a good question. Now we're shifting
a little bit if this got you all lost.
Okay, sorry about that. Anyway, here's the question.
Okay, here was the overage. Now, the overage as we said, if
it's a שדה, sade, you're allowed
seven and a half קב, and once it's, you know, and once
it's, well let's say it this way. If it's a שדה, sade,
once it's nine קב, the seller loses his prerogative. If it's a
גינה, then once it's how big?
A half of a קב. A half of a קב he loses
his prerogative. Okay, so here was a case that he sold here
a כור. kor.
This was over, this was eight קב and now the, alright so
it's an overage, it's more than the proportional amount. The seller has
his prerogative. The seller says whatever, I want to force you to
buy it. In the interim, however, before they got around to measuring
it, this plot of land actually became usable as a vegetable garden.
Maybe the guy planted this as a vegetable garden. The רשב"ם says
maybe a stream of water started flowing through it, made it more
usable. So now this plot of land, okay maybe the whole thing
is a vegetable garden. So now the seller says to the buyer,
the buyer says to the seller, nobody, you don't have a prerogative
because now this plot of land as a vegetable garden is totally
usable by itself. So you've got to take it back. If it
were a wheat field, then because it's less than the usable amount,
you have the prerogative what to do. But right now, while we
haven't got around to measuring it, it became usable as a vegetable
garden. So as a vegetable garden it's totally usable, you don't have
a prerogative and you've got to take it back. So what do
we say? Do we say that it goes by the way it
was sold and it remains the seller's prerogative? Or do we say
it goes by how it's usable now and if it's usable now
as a vegetable garden, the seller has to take it back? So
the גמרא says תיקו. teiku. We don't know. We'll have to leave
that as a standing question. Okay, תנא, tana, now here's the final
question or another one which was asked earlier. אם היה סמוך לשדהו
אפילו כל שהוא מחזיר לו קרקע. im haya samuch lesadehu afilu kol
shehu machzir lo karka. Ah,
so now this is, finally we get away from the size.
I sold you the field, this בית כור, beis kor, but this
was my plot of land here. Okay.
And it didn't matter what the intention was of the buyer, whether
he originally wanted to use it as a garden?
Yeah, I don't know. So okay, so here in this case, okay,
the point is, now when it's eight, when it's this overage, can
I say it's still my prerogative to say I'm going to force
you to buy it? Or can you say back to me, what
the heck are you talking about? The only reason חז"ל Chazal gave
you that prerogative was because what are you going to do with
a little sliver of land? But here it is just part of
your own property. You'll just move the boundary line to include that
little extra. So you can't force me to buy it. So that
makes a lot of sense. So that's what we say, אם היה
סמוך לשדהו אפילו כל שהוא מחזיר לו קרקע. im haya samuch lesadehu
afilu kol shehu machzir lo karka. Then you know, I can't force
the buyer to buy it, he gets to give me back the
land. תיבעי רב אשי, te-ba’ei Rav Ashi, so רב אשי Rav Ashi
asked, בור מהו שיפסיק? bor mahu she-kafsik? Okay, but
one minute, let's say the reason, because there was some reason that
we had drawn the boundary line here initially. Right? We said we
were talking about a defined plot of land. So maybe the reason
that we drew a boundary line there initially was because right there
in the middle
there was a well. Okay now, I don't know why so, therefore,
now I don't know exactly why that's such an issue. So what?
So I move the boundary line here and I've got a well
in the middle of my property. I don't know, but maybe you
want the well at the edge of the property or something. So
that's one question. Would that define it as, and then in case
I can say no, I can't just incorporate it into my property,
there's a well in the way. I don't really get the well
problem, but the other ones make sense. אמת המים מהו שיפסיק? ammas
hamayim mahu she-kafsik?
Let's say I've got my irrigation canal that's going down here. So,
but I guess you want the irrigation canal at the edge of
your property, not in the middle because you want to plant the
whole thing wheat. I guess that was the same about the בור's
bor well. You don't want a בור bor in the middle, you
want it at the edge. So in that case am I allowed
to say no, I can't just incorporate that, I still have a
right to force you to buy it because that would put my
irrigation canal in the middle of my field, not at the edge.
דרך הרבים מהו שיפסיק? derech harabbim mahu she-kafsik? Or let's say there
was a path that the רבים rabbim used. Or ריכפא דדיקלא מהו
שיפסיק? richpa de-dikla mahu she-kafsik?
Let's say this was a copse of trees, of palm trees. So
is it enough that it's contingent, contiguous, excuse me? Or does it
have to be like you know, with you know completely like you
know incorporatable and if there's something there physically that sort of separates
it off. Then again I can still say if it's less than
nine קב you can't, then I can choose to get that I
can choose to force you to buy it. So the גמרא by
all those says תיקו, Teiku, so we don't know the answer to
that, but at least you understand the question, okay? All right, last
piece which is very easy. ולא את הרובע בלבד מחזיר לו אלא
את כל המותר. Velo es harova bilvad machzir lo ela es kol
hamotar.
Not only do you return so in this case, right, we were
off, we were off if this was a סאה, you're allowed to
be off, you're allowed to be off a רובע, rova okay? And
instead of being off a רובע, rova, you were off, I don't
know, a רובע plus point one, okay? So the משנה Mishnah says
that now that it's more than the minimum amount, you have to
make good. So the משנה Mishnah. says, oh, you don't just return
the רובע, you return the extra, which is, which the גמרא's going
to say no, you should be saying the opposite. You don't just
return the extra that's over the רובע, once you're returning, once you've
crossed the line, you're returning the whole amount, right? So if you're
allowed to be off one and you were off by one point
one, you don't just return point one, you return one point one,
okay? But the language of the משנה Mishnah is: you don't just
return the one, you even return the point one. So the גמרא
says, huh? גמרא says כלפי לייא? Klapi laya? Like, where's that going?
Which is a way of saying that's the opposite of the way
it should be said. So okay, so we were being a little
imprecise. תני רבין בר רב נחמן: Tani Ravin bar Rav Nachman: No,
רואה המותר בלבד מחזיר לו. Ro'eh hamostar bilvad machzir lo.
You don't only return the point one, אלא את כל הרבעים כולן,
ela es kol harva'im kulan, and you return all the ones as
well, okay? So it's just, that's what the משנה Mishnah means, okay?
Not only if you're allowed to be off by a רובע and
then you were off by a רובע plus point one רובע, you
don't just return that, you return the whole amount, okay? And you
make good on the whole difference.
All right, and then we had a similar decision to our previous
discussions when there was an excess.
Yeah, so the גמרא brought this משנה in in that previous discussion.
Now we're hitting that actual משנה. Okay, so I think that all
of what, with all this huge הסברה, hasbarah, I think it was
pretty clear. The debate of רבא Rava and of רב נחמן and
רב הונא maybe got a little confusing, but again I think you
understand the issue there with whether it remains proportional or whether he
loses his prerogative once the absolute amount is a usable amount. Okay,
let's just read one the משנה and then with that we'll end
because the משנה, I was waiting for somebody to ask this, the
first משנה said if you say more less, it's this way, if
you say exact, it's the other way, and the גמרא said what
if you say nothing? And then we decided nothing was like more
or less. This משנה deals with what if you said both? You
said two contradictory languages, okay? So let's just read the משנה. מידה
בחבל אני מוכר לך הן חסר הן יתר. Mida bechevel ani mocher
lach hen chaser hen yeter. I am selling it to you exactly
by the measuring stick, more or less.
So בטל הן חסר הן יתר מידה בחבל. batel hen chaser hen
yeter mida bechevel. So this, this תנא tanna holds that if there's
contradictory language, you go by the second part of the phrase. So
the statement of more or less negates the statement of precisely, and
it's defined as more or less. So same in the reverse. If
you said הן חסר הן יתר מידה בחבל, hen chaser hen yeter
mida bechevel, I'm going to sell it to you more or
less, a בית כור beit kor measured exactly. So it says in
that case בטל מידה בחבל הן חסר הן יתר, batel mida bechevel
hen chaser hen yeter, דברי בן ננס. divrei Ben Nanas. What?
Does this bring you back to סתם? stam?
You would think, but it doesn't.
It says, it says no, if you say...
No, if you say I'm going to tell you more or less,
no, בטל batel doesn't mean they both get thrown out. בטל batel
means that this one wins. No, that's not what בטל batel means.
בטל batel means it wins. So if you say I'm going to
tell you more or less exactly, okay, so then, so then it
means exactly. That's what, now this is a very strange משנה because
it's very rare that you have דברי רבי divrei Rabbi X X
and then you don't hear the other opinion, but in the משנה
we don't hear the other opinion, the גמרא's going to quote the
other opinion. Okay, but this becomes a more broader question of if
you have contradictory language, which language dictates? And בן ננס Ben Nanas
says it's the second language that dictates, okay? So we'll see about
this tomorrow.